couple of minutes every animal was at his post.
As the human beings approached the farm buildings, Snowball launched his first attack.
All the pigeons, to the number of 35, flew to and fro over the men's heads and
muted upon them from midair.
And while the men were dealing with this, the geese, who had been hiding
behind the hedge, rushed out and pecked viciously at the calves of their legs.
However, this was only a light skirmishing maneuver intended to create
a little disorder, and the men easily drove the geese off with their sticks.
Snowball now launched his second line of attack.
Muriel, Benjamin, and all the sheep, with Snowball at the head of them,
rushed forward and prodded and butted the men from every side, while Benjamin
turned round and lashed at them with his small hoofs.
But once again, the men, with their sticks and their hobnailed boots, were too strong for them.
And suddenly, at a squeal from Snowball, which was the signal for retreat, all
the animals turned and fled through the gateway into the yard.
The men gave a shout of triumph.
They saw, as they imagined, their enemies in flight, and they rushed after them in disorder.
This was just what Snowball had intended.
As soon as they were well inside the yard, the three horses, the three cows,
and the rest of the pigs, who had been lying in ambush in the cowshed, suddenly
emerged in their rear, cutting them off.
Snowball now gave the signal for the charge.
He himself dashed straight for Jones.
Jones saw him coming, raised his gun, and fired.
The pellets scored bloody streaks along Snowball's back, and a sheep dropped dead.
Without halting for an instant, Snowball flung his 15 stone against Jones's legs.
Jones was hurled into a pile of dung, and his gun flew out of his hands.
But the most terrifying spectacle of all was Boxer, rearing up on his hind legs
and striking out with his great iron-shod hoofs like a stallion.
His very first blow took a stable-lad from Foxwood on the skull and stretched
him lifeless in the mud.
At the sight, several men dropped their sticks and tried to run.
Panic overtook them, and the next moment all the animals together were chasing
them round and round the yard.
They were gored, kicked, bitten, trampled on.
There was not an animal on the farm that did not take vengeance on them after his
own fashion.
Even the cat suddenly leaped off a roof onto a carman's shoulders and sank her
claws in his neck, at which he yelled horribly.
At a moment when the opening was clear, the men were glad enough to rush out of
the yard and make a bolt for the main road.
And so, within 5 minutes of their invasion, they were in ignominious
retreat by the same way as they had come, with a flock of geese hissing after them